Guide to the Dennis Serrette Papers WAG.316
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Dennis Serrette Papers
1969-2008
1977-2005
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Serrette, Dennis
WAG.316
7.5 Linear Feet in 15 manuscript boxes, 1 oversized flat box, 2 folders in a shared oversized box, 1 oversized flat file folder, and 3 floppy disks in a shared cassette box
0.71 Megabytes in 22 computer files
Dennis Serrette is a union activist, founding member of the Communication Workers of America (CWA) Black Caucus, and a founding member of the Coalition of Black Trade Unionists (CBTU). He was also the New Alliance Party candidate in the 1984 United States presidential election. The Dennis Serrette Papers (1969-2008) contain materials created and collected by Serrette and focus largely on his 1984 presidential campaign and his work as a union activist. Materials include sample electoral ballots, correspondence, flyers, administrative papers, newspaper articles, fundraiser invitations, speeches, conference materials, press releases, brochures, newsletters, handwritten notes, and research materials focused on Serrette's areas of interest.
Biographic Note
Dennis Serrette was born in Harlem in the 1940s and has been a union activist since 1964. In 1971, he became a founding member of the Communication Workers of America (CWA) Black Caucus. Between 1971 and 1972, while serving as vice president of the Local 1101 CWA chapter, he participated in a seven month strike against the New York Telephone Company. In 1972, he became a founding member of the Coalition of Black Trade Unionists (CBTU) and later served as president of the United Association for Labor Education (UALE).
In 1984 Serrette ran for President of the United States on the New Alliance Party ticket. At the time, Serrette was working as a switchman for the New York Telephone Company. His running mate was teacher Nancy Ross. Serrette's campaign platform called for a national health plan, limiting the use of nuclear weapons, fair housing, full employment for all, and affirmative action.
Currently, he serves as one of the CWA's Education Specialists.
Scope and Contents
The Dennis Serrette Papers (1969-2008) contain materials created and collected by Serrette and focus largely on his 1984 presidential campaign and his work as a union activist. Materials relating to Serrette's presidential campaign include sample electoral ballots, correspondence, flyers, administrative papers, statistics, reports, newspaper articles, fundraiser invitations, press releases, and speeches. Together, these materials provide insight into the types of political issues that were important to Serrette, the breadth of his campaigning, the extent of his electoral reach, and the type of events his campaign team organized.
With regards to Serrette's participation and affiliation with various labor and teaching organizations, the collection includes administrative papers, brochures, teaching materials, newsletters, conference materials, and handwritten notes that together reflect his commitment to union workers, their rights, and their education. Materials related to organizations such as United Association for Labor Education (UALE), Communication Workers of America (CWA), the CWA's Minority Leadership Institute (MLI), Black Workers for Justice (BWFJ), and the Coalition of Black Trade Unionists (CBTU) can be found in this collection. Digital versions of documents related to the UALE, MLI, the University of Michigan Labor Studies Center Black Men in Unions Institute, and American Federation of Labor and Congress of International Organizations (AFL-CIO) can also be found within this collection.
Finally, the collection contains research materials focused on Serrette's interests including socialism in Vietnam in the 1980s, Marxism, immigration, diveristy, American politics, the post-9/11 anti-war movement, domestic and international labor movements, and the African diaspora.
Arrangement
The materials in the collection are arranged in a single file listing with all material listed alphabetically by topic. Materials within each topic were also arranged alphabetically within their group.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated by Dennis Serrette, 2011. The accession numbers associated with this gift are 2010.100 and 2011.123.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Born-Digital Access Policies and Procedures
An access terminal for born-digital materials in the collection is available by appointment for reading room viewing and listening only. Researchers may view an item's original container and/or carrier, but the physical carriers themselves are not available for use because of preservation concerns.
Marxism -- History.; Research notes.; Conferences.; Correspondence.; Administrative records; Labor unions -- United States.; Peace movements; Press releases.; Labor -- History; African Americans -- History; United States -- Politics and government; Notebooks; Ballots.; Serrette, Dennis; Jackson, Jesse, 1941-; Serrette, Dennis; New Alliance Party (U.S.); National Rainbow Coalition (U.S.); Communications Workers of America; Coalition of Black Trade Unionists (U.S.); United Association for Labor Education.; Black Workers for Justice; American Federation of Labor. Congress for Industrial Organization
- Address List, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
- American Federation of Labor and Congress of International Organizations (AFL-CIO), 2001-2005; cuid42585 (Box 1, Folder 2, Box Electronic Records, E-records TW_WAG_316_ER_3)
- American Federation of Labor and Congress of International Organizations (AFL-CIO) -- Center for Working Capital, 2003 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- American Federation of Labor and Congress of International Organizations (AFL-CIO) -- Economic Education Program, 2002 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- African American Labor Leaders' Economic Summit, 2002 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Appointment Book, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- The Bar Association of the District of Columbia, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Bargaining Basic Skills: What Unions Should Know About Negotiating Worker-Centered Literacy Programs, 2000 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Beyond Diversity: Building a Class Conscious Anti-Racist Practice Workshop, 2001-2002 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Blacks in America: A Tribute to Jesse Louis Jackson, Dennis Lewis Serrette, and Black History Month, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Black Voices for Peace (BVFP), 2001 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Black Workers for Justice (BWFJ), 1985-1986, 1994, 2003 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Black Workers for Justice (BWFJ) -- Cuba, 1994-1995 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Black Workers for Justice (BWFJ) -- Justice Speaks Newsletter, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Black Workers for Justice (BWFJ) -- Worker's School, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Black Workers Unity Movement (BWUM), undated (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Burgundy Farm County Day School - Diveristy Committee, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Chinese American Workers' History (by Dennis Serrette), undated (Box 1, Folder 18)
- Citywide Crisis (cartoon by Dennis Serrette), undated (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Coalition for a Moratorium on Evictions, 1986 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Coalition of Black Trade Unionists (CBTU), 1977, 1983-1984, 2003 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Coalition of Black Trade Unionists (CBTU) -- 27th National Convention, 1998 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Coalition of Black Trade Unionists (CBTU) -- Chapter President Meeting Minutes, 2001 (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Coalition of Black Trade Unionists (CBTU) -- Executive Council Meeting, 2001 (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Coalition of Black Trade Unionists (CBTU) -- Executive Council Report, 1999 (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Coalition of Black Trade Unionists (CBTU) -- Organizing Manual, 2002 (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Committee Against the Wave of Repression in Haiti, 1984 (Box 2, Folder 9)
- Communications Workers for America (CWA), 2001-2005 (Box 2, Folder 10)
- Communications Workers for America (CWA) -- A Brief History of African American Struggle for Equality in CWA and the Telephone Company (1963 to 1985), undated (Box 2, Folder 11)
- Communications Workers for America (CWA) -- A Brief History of the Struggle for Equality by Minorities in CWA and the Telephone Company (1947 to 2000), 2001 (Box 2, Folder 12)
- Communications Workers for America (CWA) -- A Brief History of the Struggle of Minorities for Equality in CWA and the Telephone Company (1947 to 1999), undated (Box 2, Folder 13)
- Communications Workers for America (CWA) -- Committee on Equity, circa 1980s (Box 2, Folder 14)
- Communications Workers for America (CWA) -- Constitution, 2002 (Box 2, Folder 15)
- Communications Workers for America (CWA) -- CWA History: A Brief Review, 2001 (Box 2, Folder 16)
- Communications Workers for America (CWA) -- CWA News, 2001 (Box 16, Folder 2)
- Communications Workers for America (CWA) -- CWA Rates Congress, 2003 (Box 2, Folder 17)
- Communications Workers for America (CWA) -- Dennis Serrette Election Materials, undated (Box 3, Folder 1)
- Communications Workers for America (CWA) -- District One Minority Caucus International Educational Conference, 2000 (Box 3, Folder 2)
- Communications Workers for America (CWA) -- Grievance Reports, 1969, 1983 (Box 3, Folder 3)
- Communications Workers for America (CWA) --Healthcare Coordinating Council, 2002 (Box 3, Folder 4)
- Communications Workers for America (CWA) -- Larry Cohen, Globalization, and Telecommunications, 1994, 2002 (Box 3, Folder 5)
- Communications Workers for America (CWA) -- Legislative Fact Sheet, 2002 (Box 3, Folder 6)
- Communications Workers for America (CWA) -- Minority Caucus Membership Packets, 1998, 2001 (Box 3, Folder 7)
- Communications Workers for America (CWA) -- Minority Leadership Institute (MLI), 2000-2002 (Box 3, Folder 8-9)
- Communications Workers for America (CWA) -- Minority Leadership Institute (MLI) -- Conference at George Meany Center for Labor Studies, 2004 (Box 3, Folder 10)
- Communications Workers for America (CWA) -- Minority Leadership Institute (MLI) -- Correspondence, 2002 (Box 3, Folder 11)
- Communications Workers for America (CWA) -- Minority Leadership Institute (MLI) -- History and General Information, 2001-2002 (Box 4, Folder 1)
- Communications Workers for America (CWA) -- Minority Leadership Institute (MLI) -- Previous Attendees, 2002 (Box 4, Folder 2)
- Communications Workers for America (CWA) -- Minority Leadership Institute (MLI) -- Teaching Assignments, 2007; cuid42586 (Box 4, Folder 3, Box Electronic Records, E-records TW_WAG_316_ER_2)
- Communications Workers for America (CWA) -- Parliamentary Procedure, undated (Box 4, Folder 4)
- Communications Workers for America (CWA) -- Occupational Safety and Health Language in CWA Contracts: Four Model Agreements, 2001 (Box 4, Folder 5)
- Communications Workers for America (CWA) -- Rank and File Stewards Course, 1977 (Box 4, Folder 6)
- Communications Workers for America (CWA) -- Social Security or Private Insecurity, 2005 (Box 4, Folder 7)
- Communications Workers for America (CWA) -- Susan Steinman, 1985 (Box 4, Folder 8)
- Communications Workers for America (CWA) -- Treatment of Telephone Workers, 1981-1982 (Box 4, Folder 9)
- Communications Workers for America (CWA) -- Workforce Transition Project, undated (Box 4, Folder 10)
- Conference -- African American Labor Leaders' Economic Summit, 2002 (Box 4, Folder 11)
- Conference -- Eighth Annual Marxism and Mental Illness Conference, 1981-1982 (Box 5, Folder 1)
- Conference -- Fifth Annual Labor Management Symposium, 2002 (Box 5, Folder 2)
- Conference -- Generating Power for the Labor Movement, 2002 (Box 5, Folder 3)
- Conference -- New Directions for Labor, 1986 (Box 5, Folder 4)
- Conference -- Search Committee for a United Left Presidential Ticket (SCULPT), 1983 (Box 5, Folder 5)
- Conference -- U.S. Labor Against War National Labor Assembly for Peace, 2003 (Box 5, Folder 6)
- Conference -- Women's Affirmative Action Committee of the State of New Jersey, 2003 (Box 5, Folder 7)
- "Contingent Workers Fight for Fairness" (The National Alliance of Fair Employment), 2000 (Box 5, Folder 8)
- Dennis Serrette Name Plate, undated (Box 5, Folder 9)
- Dennis Serrette Presidential Campaign, 1984 (Box 5, Folder 10-11)
- Dennis Serrette Presidential Campaign -- Campaign Poster, 1984 (Box Shared Tamiment 171, Folder 3)
- Dennis Serrette Presidential Campaign -- Correspondence, 1984 (Box 5, Folder 12)
- Dennis Serrette Presidential Campaign -- National Ops Reports, 1984 (Box 6, Folder 1-4)
- Dennis Serrette Presidential Campaign -- Press, 1983-1984 (Box 6, Folder 5, Box 16, Folder 3-6)
- Dennis Serrette Presidential Campaign -- Sample Ballots and Certficates, 1984 (Box 6, Folder 6-7, Box 7, Folder 1-3, Box Shared Tamiment 171, Folder 4, Flat-file-folder 3)
- Dennis Serrette Presidential Campaign -- A Tribute to Dennis Serrette and the Independent Political Movement in Illinois, 1984 (Box 7, Folder 4)
- Dennis Serrette Presidential Campaign -- A Worker for the People (Dennis Serrette Testimonial Dinner), 1983 (Box 7, Folder 5)
- Dennis Serrette Resume, 2001 (Box 7, Folder 6)
- District Council Meetings, 2002 (Box 7, Folder 7)
- Dollars and Sense Magazine, 1983-1985 (Box 7, Folder 8)
- Economic Policy Institute -- Briefing Paper, undated (Box 7, Folder 9)
- Edmund Burke School, 2003 (Box 7, Folder 10)
- Edmund Burke School -- Board of Trustees, 2004-2005 (Box 7, Folder 11)
- Expanding Democracy - A Voter Protection Kit, 2008 (Box 8, Folder 1)
- Free Trade of the Americas (FTAA), 2002 (Box 8, Folder 2)
- George Meany National Labor College -- The Virtues of Union Ethics Training, undated (Box 8, Folder 3)
- Handwritten Notes, undated, 1981 (Box 8, Folder 4-5)
- The Harvest Institute Report, 2003 (Box 8, Folder 6)
- Highlander Research and Education Center, 2005 (Box 8, Folder 7)
- The Homesteader - Newsletter of the Harlem Reclamation Project, 1985 (Box 8, Folder 8)
- Images from a Neglected Past: The Work and Culture of the Chinese in America Exhibition, circa 1980s (Flat-file-folder 3)
- Impeach Reagan! Applaud Jackson! Vote Consumer Party! (Article by Dennis Serrette), 1983 (Box 16, Folder 1)
- Independent National Black Political Party (INBPP), 1980 (Box 8, Folder 9)
- International Union of Electric, Electrical, Salaried, Machine, and Furniture Workers (IUE), 2002 (Box 8, Folder 10)
- Jobs with Justice, 2003-2004 (Box 8, Folder 11)
- John Kerry Presidential Campaign, 2004; cuid42587 (Box 8, Folder 12, Box Electronic Records, E-records TW_WAG_316_ER_4)
- Labor Committee for Peace and Justice, 2003 (Box 8, Folder 13)
- Labor Notes, 1983, 2003 (Box 8, Folder 14)
- "Mayor Eddie Carthan Speaks to the Jury", 1982 (Box 8, Folder 15)
- Michigan Welfare Rights Organization, 2003 (Box 8, Folder 16)
- Mobilization for Survival, 1984 (Box 8, Folder 17)
- My Vote, My Right, 2004 (Box 8, Folder 18)
- National Black Communications Coalition (NBCC), 1980-1981, 1985 (Box 8, Folder 19)
- National Black Independent Party (NBIP), 1980-1981, 1988 (Box 9, Folder 1)
- National Committee to Overturn the Bakke Decision, 1978 (Box 9, Folder 2)
- New Alliance Party, 1981, 1993-1994, 2003 (Box 9, Folder 3, Box 16, Folder 7)
- New Jersey Black Issues Convention (NJBIC), 1984-1985 (Box 9, Folder 4, Box 16, Folder 8)
- The New York Mobilizer, 1984 (Box 9, Folder 5)
- New York Univeristy -- The Working Class Experience Class, 1981 (Box 9, Folder 6)
- The NewsGuild-Communication Workers of America (TNG-CWA), 2002 (Box 9, Folder 7)
- The NewsGuild-Communication Workers of America (TNG-CWA) -- 2002 Report: Diversity in the Industry and the Guild, Where Are We Today? (Box 9, Folder 8)
- Notebooks, undated (Box 9, Folder 9-11, Box 10, Folder 1)
- Organising Modules for Trade Unions: How to Increase Worker Participation in Our Unions (Public Service International), 1997 (Box 10, Folder 2)
- Organizing Notes - Campaign for Political Rights, 1980-1981 (Box 10, Folder 3)
- Peace and Freedom Party, 1982-1983 (Box 10, Folder 4)
- Peace and Freedom Revolutionary Progressives - Red Papers, 1975 (Box 10, Folder 5)
- People's Anti-war Mobilization, 1981 (Box 10, Folder 6)
- Politifest, 1984 (Box 10, Folder 7)
- Prince George County Maryland Politics, 1975, 1994, 1998 (Box 10, Folder 8, Box 16, Folder 9)
- Progressive Notes, 2002 (Box 10, Folder 9)
- Racism for Sale: Consumer Fraud in the Independent Movement (Dennis Serrette), circa 1980s (Box 10, Folder 10)
- Rainbow Alliance, 1984 (Box 10, Folder 11)
- Research Materials -- 9/11, 2001-2003 (Box 10, Folder 12)
- Research Materials -- African American Labor History, 2002 (Box 10, Folder 13)
- Research Materials -- African Diaspora, 1986, 2002, 2005 (Box 11, Folder 1)
- Research Materials -- Afro-American Liberator Newspaper, 1984-1985 (Box 16, Folder 10)
- Research Materials -- Anti-war, 1984, 2001-2003 (Box 11, Folder 2-3)
- Research Materials -- Asian American Labor History, 1995-2002 (Box 11, Folder 4)
- Research Materials -- The Communist Party of Vietnam Historical Landmarks, 1982 (Box 11, Folder 5)
- Research Materials -- Community Organizing, 1994 (Box 11, Folder 6)
- Research Materials -- Consumer Voice Newspaper, 1967, 1976, 1982 (Box 16, Folder 11)
- Research Materials -- Critical Practice: The Theoretical Journal of the International Workers Party, 1978 (Box 11, Folder 7)
- Research Materials -- Discrimination, 2002-2003 (Box 11, Folder 8)
- Research Materials -- Diversity, 2003 (Box 11, Folder 9)
- Research Materials -- Global Historical Facts, 2001-2004 (Box 11, Folder 10, Box 12, Folder 1)
- Research Materials -- Global Trade Union History, 2002-2005 (Box 12, Folder 2)
- Research Materials -- Hate Crimes, 2001 (Box 12, Folder 3)
- Research Materials -- Immigration, 2002-2003 (Box 12, Folder 4)
- Research Materials -- The Impact of Workplace Health and Safety on Black Workers: Assessment and Prognosis, 1980 (Box 12, Folder 5)
- Research Materials -- International News, 1983-1984 (Box 16, Folder 12)
- Research Materials -- Labor Movements, 1983 (Box 16, Folder 13)
- Research Materials -- Losing Your Future: How Minority Youth Are Being Left Behind by the Graduation Rate Crisis, 2004 (Box 12, Folder 6)
- Research Materials -- A Manifesto on Method: A Study of the Transformation from the Capitalist Mind to the Fascist Mind, 1974 (Box 12, Folder 7)
- Research Materials -- Marxism, undated, 1978 (Box 12, Folder 8-9)
- Research Materials -- Miminum Wage, 2000-2001 (Box 12, Folder 10)
- Research Materials -- Outsourcing Jobs Abroad, 2004 (Box 12, Folder 11)
- Research Materials -- Privatization, 1993 (Box 13, Folder 1, Box 16, Folder 14)
- Research Materials -- Race, Poverty, and the Enviroment: A Journal for Social and Enviromental Justice, 2002-2003 (Box 13, Folder 2)
- Research Materials -- South Africa and Apartheid, 1982, 1985, 1992-1995 (Box 13, Folder 3, Box 16, Folder 15)
- Research Materials -- Strategic Planning, 2006 (Box 13, Folder 4)
- Research Materials -- U.S.Intervention Abroad, 2002-2003 (Box 13, Folder 5)
- Research Materials -- U.S. Labor Movements, 2001-2003 (Box 13, Folder 6)
- Research Materials -- U.S. Politics (Bush Administration), 2002-2004 (Box 13, Folder 7)
- Reverand Jesse Jackson and the National Rainbow Coalition, 1983-1987 (Box 14, Folder 1, Box 16, Folder 16-17)
- Senator Gloria Lawlah, 2004 (Box 14, Folder 2)
- Socialist Republic of Vietnam - Permanent Mission to the United Nations, 1982-1984 (Box 14, Folder 3-4)
- The Struggle Magazine, 1977-1978 (Box 14, Folder 5)
- Technician Performance Plan, undated (Box 14, Folder 6)
- Ten Ways to Fight Hate, 2000 (Box 14, Folder 7)
- TransAfrica, 2002-2005 (Box 14, Folder 8-9)
- United Association for Labor Education (UALE), 2001-2005 (Box 14, Folder 10, Box 15, Folder 1-2)
- United Association for Labor Education (UALE) -- Crisis for the Labor Movement and for Labor Education Conference, 2005 (Box 15, Folder 3)
- United Association for Labor Education (UALE) -- Executive Board, 2002; cuid42588 (Box 15, Folder 4, Box Electronic Records, E-records TW_WAG_316_ER_5)
- United Association for Labor Education (UALE) -- September 11th: Impacts and Responses Conference, 2002 (Box 15, Folder 5)
- University of Michigan Labor Studies Center - Black Men in Unions Institute, 2003-2004; cuid42589 (Box 15, Folder 6, Box Electronic Records, E-records TW_WAG_316_ER_1)
- U.S./Vietnam Friendship Association Newsletter, 1981-1983 (Box 15, Folder 7)
- Vietnam Courier: A Monthly Review, 1982-1984 (Box 15, Folder 8-9)
- Western Electric Pittsburgh, 1973 (Box 15, Folder 10)
- Workers Policy - A Labor Journal, 1977 (Box 15, Folder 11)
- Working Together for Public Service (U.S. Secretary of Labor), 1996 (Box 15, Folder 12)
- WWRL Radio Station Correspondence, circa 1980s (Box 15, Folder 13)